You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we discover the
mighty power of oatmeal.
Did you know that
before there was insulin,
there was the ‘oatmeal cure’?
The life of many diabetics was saved
or prolonged by
Carl von Noorden’s oatmeal diet,
which he apparently
stumbled upon accidentally.
Some of his diabetic patients
had gastrointestinal issues;
so, he put them on oatmeal,
and instead of the sugars
spilling over into their urine
getting worse,
they started getting better.
He published his findings
in 1903, which was received
with a great deal of skepticism.
But the skeptics were overcome,
however, in the following years
by the weight of the evidence.
A turning point
came when a doctor
as notable as James B. Herrick
gave it a try.
Dr. Herrick is acclaimed for his
description of sickle cell anemia,
which was originally known
as Herrick's syndrome.
When Dr. Herrick began to try out
the oatmeal diet on his patients,
he was very skeptical, but was
astonished by the results.
Intense skepticism
was how Herrick put it.
His first experience
in prescribing it
was far from encouraging.
After taking one or two meals,
the patient said,
“Doctor, I will die before I taste
another spoonful of that oatmeal mush.”
And indeed, tragically, she did.
Other doctors echoed
patient reticence
to tolerate so monotonous
an equine diet.
But in general, Herrick said,
he went on to experience
little difficulty
in putting patients
on the oatmeal diet
and in keeping them
there for a few weeks.
And nothing, he reported,
was more surprising
or more gratifying than
the salutary effects he witnessed
of the oatmeal diet
in diabetes of the young,
leading to the 1909 proclamation
that no case of juvenile
or adolescent diabetes
should be deprived
of the benefits
of the oatmeal cure.
The great Elliott Joslin,
founder of the oldest
and largest diabetes clinic
in the world,
described the effects of the oatmeal
as sometimes magical,
describing the oatmeal cure
as an unsolved mystery,
referred to back
then as one
of the greatest puzzles
in diabetes.
They did have
some clues though.
They found that animal protein
had to be strictly excluded,
as it annihilates the favorable
action of oatmeal-type diets.
They used to use eggs
with the oatmeal diet,
but they got better results
without them.
And now we know, over
a century later that indeed,
animal protein intake
intensiﬁes insulin resistance,
which is the cause of prediabetes
and type 2 diabetes,
whereas plant-based foods
enhance insulin sensitivity,
which is the opposite.
Animal-protein intake
is not just associated
with insulin resistance
and a clear association
with an increased risk
of type 2 diabetes
(and this included animal protein
from meat, dairy, and ﬁsh—
higher insulin resistance and risk
of prediabetes and type 2 diabetes).
But not just an association;
you can put it to the test.
Swapping in beans for beef
improves cardiometabolic risk factors.
And it doesn’t take much.
Replace just two servings
of red meat with lentils, chickpeas,
split peas, or beans
a few days a week,
and you can significantly improve
fasting blood sugars and insulin levels,
along with the improvements
you’d expect,
like lowering of cholesterol
and triglycerides.
Based on over a dozen
randomized controlled trials,
even just swapping
like a third of protein
from animal to plant sources
can significantly improve
blood sugar control.
What’s the difference
between animal protein
and plant protein?
We think it’s the branched-chain
amino acids
concentrated in animal protein.
How do we know branched-chain
amino acids are playing a role?
Because if you give vegans
branched-chain amino acid supplements,
you can make them as insulin
resistant as meat eaters.
Their insulin sensitivity dropped
to the level resembling omnivores
and only improved again
after stopping the supplements.
But wait a second.
I thought insulin resistance stems
from excess accumulation of fat
inside your muscle cells,
particularly saturated fat.
Insulin resistance
directly correlates
with increased saturated fat
inside your muscles.
I’ve got tons of videos on this,
but basically you can
show a substantial
and consistent impairment
of insulin action,
substantial and
consistent insulin resistance
after just a single day
consuming a diet high
in saturated fat.
In fact, even a single meal
rich in saturated fat
reduces insulin sensitivity.
A single dose of butter,
for example,
impairs insulin sensitivity
even in healthy subjects.
And over time,
reducing cholesterol
and fat intake may even enhance
the ability of your pancreas
to pump out insulin
in the first place.
Now, the saturated fat
getting lodged in your muscles
may come from the foods
going into your mouth,
or if you have
excess abdominal fat,
from previous meals spilling
over into your blood stream.
But either way, what does
animal protein have to do with it?
It turns out a branched-chain
amino acid breakdown product
appears to stimulate fat uptake
and accumulation inside
the muscle cells.
But oatmeal doesn’t have any
saturated animal fat or animal protein.
Okay, but neither does
any plant food.
Why might oatmeal work
particularly well?
That’s the question
I explore next.
It is now widely accepted
that diets high in animal fat
and processed foods are
an important risk factor
for development
of type 2 diabetes.
And it’s not just animal fat,
but animal protein intake
intensiﬁes insulin resistance,
which predisposes
people to type 2 diabetes.
No wonder studies have shown
that elevated consumption
of animal products and low intake
of unprocessed plant foods
increases the risk of not only
cardiovascular disease but diabetes.
But of all the whole plant foods
to pick, why choose oatmeal
to treat diabetes, which, as I
discussed in my last video,
was used for the treatment of diabetes
before insulin was discovered.
We’ve long known that higher consumption
of whole grains, including oats,
is associated with a lower risk
of diabetes, but you don’t know...
until you put it to the test.
There have been over a dozen
randomized controlled trials
looking at the metabolic effects
of oats intake in patients
with type 2 diabetes,
and oats were found
to significantly improve
both short-term blood sugar control
and long-term blood sugar control
in addition to lowering
cholesterol levels.
We think the benefits arise
from a fermentable ﬁber in oats
called beta glucan, because you
can get cholesterol-lowering
even if you just give
the oat fiber straight,
as well as an improvement
in blood sugar control
and insulin sensitivity
in both type 2 diabetics,
as well as type 1 diabetics.
How exactly does
the fiber do that?
Well, we know one of the underlying
cholesterol-lowering mechanisms
of oatmeal consumption might be
its microbiome-manipulating ability,
in other words, having
a beneficial effect
on our intestinal bacteria.
The anti-inflammatory effects
of the short-chain fatty acids
that our good gut flora
make from fiber.
There are dozens of randomized
controlled trials
showing the types
of fiber found in oats
and beans can improve long-term
blood sugar control in diabetics—
in fact, nearly double
the FDA threshold
required for new blood sugar-
lowering drugs. Why?
Because the gut bacteria selectively
promoted by dietary fiber intake
can help alleviate
type 2 diabetes.
In fact, on the basis of 50 distinct
bacterial markers of the feces,
you can tell who does
and does not have diabetes.
But change your diet,
and you can change
your gut flora within one day.
We feed them with fiber,
and in return,
they feed us right back
with these short-chain fatty acids
like butyrate that have
all these wonderful effects.
Put people on a diet packed with oats,
beans, fruits, vegetables, and nuts,
and the number
of fiber-feeders
churning out the beneficial short-
chain fatty acids shoots up,
and fasting diabetic blood sugars
drop about 25 percent within one month.
And the more fiber-
feeders they fostered,
the better their
blood sugar control.
When the fiber-promoted
short-chain fatty acid producers
were present in greater
diversity and abundance,
participants had better improvement
in their hemoglobin A1c levels
(which is a measure of
longer-term blood sugar control).
Then, before and after
fecal transplant studies
helped nail down
cause and effect.
The oat fiber itself has been
shown to act as a prebiotic,
boosting the growth
of beneficial bacteria
like lactobacillus
and bifidobacteria.
So, between the lack
of animal protein,
lack of animal fat,
and bursting at the seams
with prebiotic fiber,
it’s no wonder that oatmeal
diets grew to become
part of the clinical routine
in the treatment of diabetics.
However, over time,
this practice
has later become
increasingly forgotten,
a disappearance that’s been
compared to the fate
of unpopular theories
in successive editions
of Soviet encyclopedias.
Despite advances in therapy,
we still have many people
with poorly controlled diabetes.
Thankfully this
forgotten tool is back.
I’ll review all the new
oatmeal diet studies next.
Thousands of years ago in ancient Egypt,
diabetes was described
as a “too great emptying of urine”
or, more poetically,
as being “like the River Nile
between the thighs.”
The recommended remedy,
ironically, was a diet
consisting of wheat grains,
grapes, honey, and berries.
The guy who coined the term
“diabetes” about 500 years later
also prescribed
a high-carbohydrate diet.
Then, right up until
we had insulin,
doctors were saving the lives
of diabetics with an oatmeal diet.
This wouldn’t make any sense
until Sir Harold Himsworth arrived
on the scene, the first
to separate out type 1 diabetes
from type 2 diabetes and define
this concept of insulin resistance.
After just a few days
on a high-fat diet,
you can get twice the blood
sugar spike in response
to drinking sugar water,
compared to after eating
a high-carb diet.
Now that type 2 diabetes is like
the Black Death of the 21st century
in terms of devastating
health impacts,
what about revisiting
the almost forgotten,
short-term dietary oatmeal
intervention as an economical,
yet—spoiler alert—
highly effective tool to achieve
better blood sugar control
in patients with type 2 diabetes?
Basically, patients
are offered up to about
two and a half cups of oatmeal
three times a day
as their meals
with nothing but some herbs
and maybe small amounts of raw
vegetables just to mix things up.
For how long?
Just a couple of days.
Note that’s only
like a thousand calories;
so, the result is a hypocaloric,
plant-based dietary intervention
that is low in fat—in fact,
no added fat—no salt,
and excludes animal protein.
Is a few days
of oatmeal really going
to make much
of a difference?
Check out this case report
of an oatmeal intervention
for severe insulin
resistance in the ICU.
Within 48 hours of admission,
the patient developed
such severe insulin
resistance she required
more than 200 units
of insulin per day.
Up until then, the patient received
standard diabetic tube feeds,
which obviously
were not working.
So instead, they dropped oatmeal
and vegetables down the tube instead,
presumably using
a really good blender.
And lo and behold, it worked.
But you've got
to see the numbers.
Yeah, her first blood sugars
of the day dropped
from up around 250 down to about
100 five days later.
But that near-normal blood sugar
was on 160 fewer units of insulin,
down from over 200 units a day.
Lower blood sugars
on 160 fewer units of insulin!
Okay, I can see how if you’re
trying to save a life in the ICU,
an oatmeal diet
can be near-miraculous.
But just in regular diabetics,
what good is eating
oatmeal for a few days
if you just go back
to your regular diet?
Several studies have suggested
that the beneficial effects
could last like a month
after the few days of oatmeal.
For example, in this randomized
controlled crossover trial
not only did insulin needs drop
about 40 percent in just two days
compared to just
restricting calories alone
with a hypocaloric
diabetic diet,
but also a measure
long-term blood sugar control
taken four weeks later
reflected the benefit.
So, we’re talking a highly
significant reduction
of required daily
insulin doses
with beneficial effects
shown weeks later.
Who cares if you have to take
huge doses of insulin though?
Because insulin causes weight gain,
which just makes the underlying
insulin resistance worse.
So, it’s like this vicious cycle.
But instead, with the oatmeal
you’re actually treating the cause,
not to mention the incidence
of cancer and overall mortality
associated with having
such high levels of insulin
in your body all the time.
Other new studies have
shown the same thing.
Two days of oatmeal significantly
reducing the required amount
of insulin and
improved blood sugar levels
with beneficial effects
noted for up to four weeks.
For example, here.
Patients with uncontrolled
type 2 diabetes,
with the two-day
oatmeal diet
leading to a 40 percent
reduction of insulin dose,
accompanied with almost
normalization of average blood sugars.
Although the intervention
only lasted for two days,
they observed a lasting significant
reduction of insulin dosage
and ameliorated mean
blood sugars for weeks
after they were dismissed
from the study.
And this was after they resumed
their regular diets.
Look at this.
A massive drop in insulin needs
after the oatmeal for two days,
but look, a month later
they were still needing
like 40 percent less insulin.
Wait a second.
How could this short intervention lead
to such dramatic results
that somehow continue on for weeks?
Although short-term dietary
oatmeal interventions
cannot be compared to whole food,
plant-based diets
in terms of maximizing
the intake of protective foods—
I mean that’s ideally
what people should try to eat
to reverse their
type 2 diabetes completely—
but they both strictly
exclude the animal-based foods
that seem to increase the risk
of developing diabetes.
So, even cutting out
saturated fat for like two days
may so reduce insulin
resistance you can free ride
on that for at least a few weeks,
even if you go back to eating crap.
WARNING, though.
If you try this oatmeal diet,
your physician has to be ready
to rapidly deprescribe
your blood sugar drugs else
you become dangerously overmedicated.
Imagine if this woman was still
getting 200 units of insulin.
Her sugars would crash
so low she’d be dead.
So, oatmeal interventions
should not be performed
in patients that might
have difficulties
in reporting symptoms
of low blood sugars,
who you can’t
closely monitor.
So, the downside
of trying oatmeal days
is that it may
work a little too well;
so, it must be done under close
medical supervision.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.